<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Science on Mirantibus</title>
    <link>/tags/science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Science on Mirantibus</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 20:06:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How not to tackle a crisis.</title>
      <link>/posts/how-not-to-tackle-a-crisis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 20:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/how-not-to-tackle-a-crisis/</guid>
      <description>Almost 2 years ago, I began a compulsory sustainability course as part of my degree. In modern times, this isn&amp;rsquo;t such a strange thing to do; it&amp;rsquo;s important that we tackle the climate problem head-on and you can&amp;rsquo;t do that if you don&amp;rsquo;t understand it. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to think &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rsquo;s there to learn about?&amp;rdquo;, after all, we all know that CO2 and Methane emissions are causing the earth to warm and the climate to change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Climate Crisis Response.</title>
      <link>/posts/the-climate-crisis-response/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 21:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/the-climate-crisis-response/</guid>
      <description>In a small bay, on the northern side of the southwestern tip of England, not too far from lands&amp;rsquo; end. The usually quiet and quaint town of Hayle has become a flurry of activity with Boris Johnson hosting 7 other countries and representatives from the EU and UN for informal talks in order to address the day&amp;rsquo;s issues. By far the most important issue this year, as in other recent years; is the climate crisis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Space Race.</title>
      <link>/posts/space-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2019 21:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/space-race/</guid>
      <description>Today we will be looking into the history of spaceflight and how it has been developing aggressively more recently.
A short history of rocketry and spaceflight. Rockets first began as an invention in 13th Century China under the Song dynasty when they were used as incendiary weapons by the Chinese navy. It wasn’t until the early 19th century however that the western world adopted rockets as a military weapon when the &amp;ldquo;Congreve rocket&amp;rdquo; was developed by Sir William Congreve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going Nuclear.</title>
      <link>/posts/going_nuclear/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/going_nuclear/</guid>
      <description>Today we will be looking at the history of nuclear energy and how it may help us in the future. From the discovery of nuclear fission to its more attractive cousin: nuclear fusion, today we learn the ins and outs of the atomic realm.
Nuclear Fission, a short history. Let’s start our journey with possibly one of the most important discoveries of the 20th century: Nuclear Fission. Nuclear Fission was first discovered in 1938 in Berlin after 50 years of research into radioactivity, which naturally broadened into what is now known as nuclear physics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
