<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics on Mirantibus</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/tags/politics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Politics on Mirantibus</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 21:59:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//localhost:1313/tags/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Climate Crisis Response.</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/the-climate-crisis-response/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 21:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/the-climate-crisis-response/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/g7-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a small bay, on the northern side of the southwestern tip of England, not too far from lands&amp;rsquo; end. The usually quiet and quaint town of Hayle has become a flurry of activity with Boris Johnson hosting 7 other countries and representatives from the EU and UN for informal talks in order to address the day&amp;rsquo;s issues. By far the most important issue this year, as in other recent years; is the climate crisis. The UK has possibly committed to the most ambitious climate actions in the world, but will these plans be carried out and can the UK lead the way into a greener future?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/g7-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a small bay, on the northern side of the southwestern tip of England, not too far from lands&amp;rsquo; end. The usually quiet and quaint town of Hayle has become a flurry of activity with Boris Johnson hosting 7 other countries and representatives from the EU and UN for informal talks in order to address the day&amp;rsquo;s issues. By far the most important issue this year, as in other recent years; is the climate crisis. The UK has possibly committed to the most ambitious climate actions in the world, but will these plans be carried out and can the UK lead the way into a greener future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK has committed to possibly the most ambitious climate goal in the world, to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/uk-enshrines-new-target-in-law-to-slash-emissions-by-78-by-2035&#34;&gt;reduce its emissions by 78% by 2035 compared to 1990 levels&lt;/a&gt;. This is set to include international travel and shipping emissions and further commits the UK to its goal of becoming carbon neutral by 2050. The government have also planned to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-takes-historic-step-towards-net-zero-with-end-of-sale-of-new-petrol-and-diesel-cars-by-2030&#34;&gt;ban the sale and manufacture of new petrol and diesel engine cars by 2030 and hybrid cars by 2035&lt;/a&gt;. This is obviously a big step forward in the fight against climate change and for a more sustainable society, especially when it is considered that the UK maintains strong diplomatic ties with the commonwealth, the US and the EU (to some extent), putting it in a prime position to encourage other countries, poor and wealthy to follow suit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If, however, the government which has made these big promises, is indeed so committed to the reduction in emissions and the slowing of climate change and global warming; then it has made some other, rather confusing steps which seem contradictory to this message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015 the last operating coal mine in the UK &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-york-north-yorkshire-35803048&#34;&gt;closed its pits&lt;/a&gt; and was later capped off, this was seen by many as the end of coal mining all together. In January of this year however, Cumbria County council &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-cumbria-55561852&#34;&gt;approved the plans&lt;/a&gt; for a new deep coal mine to begin construction; a plan that should have been outright rejected by 10 Downing street if they were indeed serious about the reduction of emissions. Instead a public inquiry was set up after a government U-turn following major backlash from environmental groups. Initially &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-55668507&#34;&gt;the government welcomed the announcement&lt;/a&gt; of the plans, the complete opposite of the appropriate response considering their commitments in the Paris agreement and more recent announcements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/kellingly-colliery.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Kellingly Colliery miners&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of the governments seemingly contradictory policy on climate which has attracted the attention of climate groups and campaigners is that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2021/mar/24/uk-government-to-allow-new-north-sea-oil-and-gas-exploration&#34;&gt;the government plans to continue to allow new wells to be drilled&lt;/a&gt; in the north sea for oil and gas exploration. As well as the governments reduction on air travel passenger duty for domestic travel and its refusal to invest substantially in rail travel which would take both cars off the road and planes out of the sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Possibly worst of all is that the government has in recent times &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-57379699&#34;&gt;cut the foreign aid budget&lt;/a&gt; from £14 Billion to around £10 Billion, which could significantly handicap smaller nations in their ability to respond to the climate crisis and lead them to rely on fossil fuels as an energy source. If we are to recover from the crisis that we find ourselves in then we need to help smaller countries to stop emitting rather than shifting the blame to them. It is already well known that it is much easier to be sustainable the richer you are; this rings especially true on the scale of nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This apparent failure of the government seems to have culminated in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/jun/13/johnsons-g7-after-all-the-hype-what-was-actually-achieved&#34;&gt;disappointment for many&lt;/a&gt; after the end of the G7 summit where it was widely expected that firm deals would emerge rather than vague promises. The government said that it was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/jun/13/johnsons-g7-after-all-the-hype-what-was-actually-achieved&#34;&gt;waiting until the G20 and COP26 summits&lt;/a&gt; later this year to make these financial and legal commitments, however it remains to be seen if they will be true to their word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/g7-3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll finish this post by stressing the immense importance of the way in which we continue to strive towards sustainability, the UK has a real chance here to be a leader in the climate response. Just today Oxfam released a report that made clear that the economic impact of a climate disaster, for which we are heading, would wipe $7 Trillion off of the economies of the G7 alone. For that reason and for many more, let&amp;rsquo;s hope that the government intends to keep its promises and insist that they exceed their goals not just reach them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit: Since this post, there has also been a commitment from the G7 to take stricter measures on Coal-fired power plants; closing down plants that don&amp;rsquo;t incorporate carbon capture technology. We have of course yet to see if this has any effect on emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Chico Demmenie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Re-Uploaded &amp;amp; Edited 30/09/2022]&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The good in us all: why we should trust people more.</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/the-good-in-us-all/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2020 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/the-good-in-us-all/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/rutgerbregman.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34; title=&#34;Rutger Bregman&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I read a book by the Dutch historian Rutger Bregman, called &amp;ldquo;Human Kind: A hopeful history&amp;rdquo;. The book is about human nature, the underlying features that shape us and how we are affected by civilisation or perhaps how civilisation is shaped by our nature. The book systematically goes through each aspect of human nature, each example of our collective nature that you may think is true and then shows you how it can be reversed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/rutgerbregman.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34; title=&#34;Rutger Bregman&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I read a book by the Dutch historian Rutger Bregman, called &amp;ldquo;Human Kind: A hopeful history&amp;rdquo;. The book is about human nature, the underlying features that shape us and how we are affected by civilisation or perhaps how civilisation is shaped by our nature. The book systematically goes through each aspect of human nature, each example of our collective nature that you may think is true and then shows you how it can be reversed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;humankind-a-hopeful-history&#34;&gt;Humankind: A hopeful history.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have often wondered if there wasn&amp;rsquo;t a better way of organising society than the current one, one where there are more incentives than money. It was immediately clear that a completely open market wouldn&amp;rsquo;t work, there is a good reason for the business regulations that already exist; without them people and businesses have a tendency not to take others in society into consideration, creating problems such as water pollution like in the case of DuPont (Rich, 2016) or mistreating workers as many companies still do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this book, Bregman lays out and systematically discredits, the proof for the cynical conception that most people have of humankind having an underlying bad and selfish nature, a trend that mostly began with one man; Thomas Hobbes. The English philosopher theorised that the only thing that held people back from ruthlessly killing and beating each other was the thin layer of civilisation that we had managed to create. These ideas were later developed into books such as &amp;lsquo;Lord of the flies&amp;rsquo; by William Golding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bregman, however, shows a different side to humans; he looks back to the societies that existed before the advent of agriculture and finds that, usually, the groups of nomads that existed in that time frame had little or no fights whatsoever. These groups never had massive wars and hardly ever any sort of social structure, in fact, they often actively resisted it. If there was ever any type of leader, they were there because of expertise or a particular experience that they could offer the group. Despite sometimes choosing a leader, the decisions were always made together as a group and never individually. If the leader began to act on his own accord or in a way that was not liked within the group they were quickly deposed and removed from the group (Bregman, 2019. p128 - 129).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These observations of prehistoric tribes and nomadic groups come largely from observation of still unchanged tribes and archaeological evidence. There are some groups still in existence today who are so isolated from the world that they find even the slightest violence vulgar and could not comprehend that one person could ever intentionally kill another (Bregman, 2019. p128).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-effect-of-our-own-image&#34;&gt;The effect of our own image.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The historian also remarks on the effect that this view of ourselves has on society, remarking that it&amp;rsquo;s like a nocebo effect. The very idea that civilisation is the only thing that makes us good people, turns society into something that constantly is trying to stop people from hurting themselves and each other, often causing issues rather than solving them. Almost every governmental institution in the world today exists not because it trusts people or to make sure that people have some dignity but to &amp;ldquo;protect society&amp;rdquo; or to punish them for things that are deemed criminal. Instead of treating the underlying things that drive people towards criminality, for example, we punish them for it rather than reforming them away from it, almost always only exacerbating the problem further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/prison.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34; title=&#34;A Norwegian Prison&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This philosophy has already been at work in places such as the Norwegian prison system, where inmates are often afforded everyday luxuries, allowed to continue or start a line of education or work jobs around the prison. They are also encouraged to cook for themselves and learn life skills that will help them on the outside. This often goes alongside counselling if it&amp;rsquo;s needed as well as friendship; often the guards talk and make friends with the inmates. This all obviously comes with a cost; Norway spends nearly £100,000 per prisoner, compared to roughly £40,000 in the UK (BBC, 2019). This does, however significantly reduce the country&amp;rsquo;s recidivism rate to only 20% meaning that the number of inmates per capita is much lower and they ultimately also spend less on the prison system both per capita and overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-things-are-different-in-trust-based-systems&#34;&gt;How things are different in trust-based systems.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of trust-based system is adaptable to almost anything in life; take businesses for example. In the Netherlands (Bregman&amp;rsquo;s home country), there is a home care organisation called &amp;ldquo;Buurtzorg&amp;rdquo;, set up by Jos de Blok. This is not a traditional company, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any central control, no managers and no real authority. They just have people, which are divided into groups, each of around 10 - 15 nursing staff who come together every day to discuss what the plan is and if anything needs to be addressed. The group then splits into 2 person teams and helps people at home, with an emphasis on providing support and access to local resources so that the person can try to be as self-sufficient and independent as possible. The teams don&amp;rsquo;t get input from the outside, decide salaries from inside the group and only get help if they need it. Other than that there is a single financial department that handles finances but no HR, Marketing or purchasing departments as each group does this themselves (Bregman, 2019. Ch 13, pt 4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This organisation has grown to over 10,000 employees in 850 groups, other than that the effect that this model has had is difficult to quantify. So let&amp;rsquo;s instead take the example of FAVI, a french auto part manufacturer which in the 1980&amp;rsquo;s implemented a similar policy. The managerial staff were told to take a step back from the workers (in fact the first thing that happened was that the window from the upstairs office into the workshop was bricked over), and the workers were organised into teams, this time of 25 - 30. The punch clock that kept the workers&amp;rsquo; hours was promptly thrown out and the bonus system was also abandoned. Each team got control over their own salaries, work hours, contractors, suppliers and pretty much anything else they needed. They were responsible for their own clients and once the managers retired, they weren&amp;rsquo;t replaced. The managerial role was only really needed if a team asked for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be a lot of people out there, especially proponents of a completely open market who would think that this would drive a company into the ground and sow panic and disarray among employees. Instead, the profits went up dramatically, the company quintupled (Multiplied by 5) their employees, they took over 50% of their market and the production time of their most important part went from 11 days to just 1 (Bregman, 2019. Ch 13, pt 4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/jos-de-blok.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34; title=&#34;Jos de Blok&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-is-what-modern-democracy-looks-like&#34;&gt;This is what modern democracy looks like.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where the ideas that the writer discusses take a particularly interesting turn; he brings us to the idea of direct democracy. Often, the reason that even our democracies are quite flawed is because they don&amp;rsquo;t represent the prevailing sentiment among the people they purport to represent. The question is why do we only get to vote on the ideas we want to bring forward once every 4 or 5 years? And why does it require us to bring forward one singular person to lead us. This, in particular, is problematic, there is plenty of research that shows that people in elevated positions of power (even small ones) suffer a drop in IQ and certain tendencies similar to acquired sociopathy; such as impulsiveness, recklessness, egoism, arrogance and narcissism (Bregman, 2019. p 278).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the question is &amp;ldquo;How do we remedy such issues?&amp;rdquo;, then the answer could be through direct democracy. In 2004, in a small Venezuelan city called Torres; a new major took office, he was little known and had no experience, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t thought that he would even have a chance between the corrupt former mayor and the ally of Hugo Chávez. His only campaign promise? To give all of the power and money that was given to him straight back to the people of Torres. So with 35.6% of the vote and only one policy Julio Chávez (No relation) won the office of mayor. The first thing to sort was the city budget, 100% of it was to be decided by the people of Torres and they immediately used their newfound power to dismantle the systems of corruption that had been built by the career politicians that came beforehand. More than 15 years later and the community has never given up the power again, the neighborhoods look better, there is a better local economy and more importantly; there is record participation in the newly formed democratic system. Every year to this day more than 15,000 people gather in 560 communities to discuss and decide their yearly budget (Bregman, 2019. Ch 15, pt 1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real question then is how can we best implement this system on a larger scale and in a good and fair way. Let&amp;rsquo;s take the current most accepted version of democracy within a state system that there is, that of 3 branches; Legislative, Executive and Judicial. Obviously, the legislative is currently the most democratic being a body made up of representatives that are decided in elections, it also is, therefore, the easiest to replace. A single website that allows for debate and voting on legislative proposals and amendments can be easily made, mix in some statistics and facts about each proposal and it looks like a working democratic system. Some other functions are harder to replace in the legislature; such as parliamentary committees and the review committees of parliamentary bills and amendments which will still have to hold elected officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Judiciary branch is somewhat more difficult as it certainly can&amp;rsquo;t be replaced entirely. The court system is somewhat fair with the noticeable exception of the judge. One idea that may fare better is a judicial pool of legal experts like the jury who would have to discuss and vote on a motion in the court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have left the most difficult for last; the Executive branch, the coveted president, prime minister or supreme dictator of each country. There is certainly a point to be made that this branch is not even needed. Certainly, I believe that budgets for example should be made by the legislature rather than the executive, but are there some things that need to be decided by one person? The main thing that comes to mind is decisions about state secrets and the military; such problems would, by nature, need a small number of people to make decisions due to the nature of those domains. I suppose the larger question, then, is do we need a military or intelligence service at all? That is a really difficult question to answer, we&amp;rsquo;re certainly not in a position of war and we live in the most peaceful time in history. I suppose if we could adopt this kind of model across the globe, then having a military at all shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be necessary but until that happens it might be, which leaves the executive branch with a big question mark above it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-conclusion&#34;&gt;In Conclusion.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is what the world might look like if we all trusted each other a little more. We could have a prison system that reforms rather than exacerbates, a justice system that is truly free and fair and a legislature that stops making universally unpopular decisions. I got almost all of the ideas from Bregman&amp;rsquo;s book, I highly recommend it. He goes into a lot more detail about the nature of humans and offers many more examples. I have been trying to change my outlook on life in the way that he recommends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Chico Demmenie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/stories-48885846&#34;&gt;BBC (2019) &amp;ldquo;How Norway turns criminals into good neighbors&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bregman R. (2019) &amp;ldquo;Human Kind: A new history&amp;rdquo; 13 ed. The Correspondent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/10/magazine/the-lawyer-who-became-duponts-worst-nightmare.html&#34;&gt;Rich N. (2016) &amp;ldquo;The lawyer who became DuPont&amp;rsquo;s worst nightmare&amp;rdquo; The New York Times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Re-Uploaded &amp;amp; Edited 30/09/2022]&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going Nuclear.</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/going_nuclear/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/going_nuclear/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/dims-1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we will be looking at the history of nuclear energy and how it may help us in the future. From the discovery of nuclear fission to its more attractive cousin: nuclear fusion, today we learn the ins and outs of the atomic realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;nuclear-fission-a-short-history&#34;&gt;Nuclear Fission, a short history.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start our journey with possibly one of the most important discoveries of the 20th century: Nuclear Fission. Nuclear Fission was first discovered in 1938 in Berlin after 50 years of research into radioactivity, which naturally broadened into what is now known as nuclear physics. This research includes the discoveries and works of legendary physicist Ernest Rutherford who famously discovered the structure of the atom in 1911.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/dims-1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we will be looking at the history of nuclear energy and how it may help us in the future. From the discovery of nuclear fission to its more attractive cousin: nuclear fusion, today we learn the ins and outs of the atomic realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;nuclear-fission-a-short-history&#34;&gt;Nuclear Fission, a short history.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start our journey with possibly one of the most important discoveries of the 20th century: Nuclear Fission. Nuclear Fission was first discovered in 1938 in Berlin after 50 years of research into radioactivity, which naturally broadened into what is now known as nuclear physics. This research includes the discoveries and works of legendary physicist Ernest Rutherford who famously discovered the structure of the atom in 1911.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1917 Rutherford was to be the first to observe a nuclear reaction, that is the use of a decaying material to transform the nucleus of another atom. He had directed an alpha particle towards a nitrogen atom, causing a single proton to split from the nucleus and transforming the atom into one of oxygen. Despite a few clear differences between this and actual nuclear fission with heavy elements, this would become known as the modest beginning of a nuclear age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took until 1934 for the Italian physicist Enrico Fermi to ‘bombard’ uranium with neutrons, concluding that the experiment had created two new elements with 93 and 94 protons respectively. This discovery was then picked up by Otto Hahn, Lise Meitner and Fritz Strassmann at what is now the free university of Berlin, who also began running experiments to try to confirm the discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During one particular experiment, Otto Hahn had stumbled upon a rather strange result; after bombarding uranium with neutrons they had found evidence of an element that bore similar characteristics to barium. This discovery was particularly odd as barium was almost half of the weight of a uranium atom and thus far no person had ever observed more than one or two protons separate from a nucleus, most physicists at the time believed that atomic nuclei could never decay that much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After seeing what many would simply write off as an anomaly; Hahn suggested that perhaps the nucleus had ‘burst’, despite being unsure if such an occurrence was even theoretically possible. After much deliberation, Meitner and Fritz concluded that Hahn’s theory must have been right and they called it ‘Fission’, after the way that cells divide by splitting in a process called ‘Binary fission’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, on the 22nd of December 1938, the trio informed the ‘Naturwissenschaften‘, a peer-reviewed science journal, of their discovery. Hahn would, for his part in the discovery receive the Nobel prize for Chemistry in 1944.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the Meitner team’s discovery, the allied scientists of Britain, Canada and the US would use the process of fission to create a bomb more powerful than anything any person on the planet at the time could have imagined. This single discovery set off a chain of events that would influence almost all other aspects of life. During the post-war period, visionaries even foresaw that nuclear reactors would power everything and anything, big or small, and the strategic use of threats of using the almighty power of the bomb led to widespread fears that the world would tear itself apart, even to this day those very fears are played upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/dims.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future-of-nuclear-fission&#34;&gt;The Future of Nuclear Fission.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last 80 years or so, there have been many different discoveries linked to nuclear fission. Since its early phase where we were promised a new future where everything was powered by the atom, the public has become quite alienated by the disasters of Chernobyl and Fukushima, not to mention the constant threat of nuclear war by the major world powers. This alienation is very much warranted as the current use of Uranium and Plutonium is, although not as dangerous as people seem to think, still not foolproof as we have proven time and time again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of a safe culture which has to be cultivated around the business of nuclear energy production, in its current form, is really worrying. The previously mentioned nuclear disasters have inspired many books, films and television series, most recently the HBO series ‘Chernobyl’, which play on the fears of the public surrounding nuclear energy. As I said, I do think that some of this scepticism is justified as with a fission reaction, the operator is constantly trying to manage and slow down the reaction which, if let out of control, can produce a meltdown or spread of serious radiation, not to mention the problem of nuclear waste and possible leaking of radioactive material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these very serious concerns and problems with the nuclear industry, it still seems to be the most effective way to transition away from fossil fuels. It has, despite all odds continued to be the energy source that has the lowest carbon footprint, beating even solar and wind, and it also has the lowest death toll of all the energy sources despite its public image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we ever want to restore our planet and save it from irreversible damage from global warming and climate change, which will only accelerate exponentially if we continue to burn coal, gas and oil in the fashion that we are currently, then nuclear power seems to be the only way to go at this point in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this need, however, nobody seems willing to spend the money to develop the technology further and we are still closing down nuclear plants around the world at a record rate, ironically the recess in power supply that this causes is being picked up by the much less sustainable and more dangerous and environmentally damaging fossil fuel energies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;even-better-alternatives&#34;&gt;Even better alternatives.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although nuclear reactors are already the safest, cleanest and most reliable source of energy, which also produces the least amount of toxic waste, that we have, they can still be vastly improved. There are still inherent problems that need to be fixed, for instance, the waste that is produced, the radiation that both the process and the waste emit and cost &amp;amp; scale of the nuclear power plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the golden age of nuclear power, the Oak ridge national laboratory in Tennessee began running an experiment that was aimed at looking into the feasibility of a new kind of nuclear reactor that used a new kind of fuel: Thorium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Molten Salt Reactor Experiment (MSRE) was an experiment that ran from 1964 until 1969, exploring the possibility of thorium powered molten salt reactors. The experiment was shut down due to a lack of funding from the US government but ultimately proved not only that a thorium reactor was possible, but that it was safer, the fuel was cheaper and the waste would have a half-life many thousands of years shorter than that of uranium and plutonium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though thorium is very obviously a better fuel choice, a fact that many companies, scientists and governments across the globe knew: we still chose to use enriched uranium which we could use to create nuclear weapons. We spent our time and resources creating a fuel supply that would give us the weapons that we all fear today, while we also neglected a cheaper, more abundant, less dangerous and ultimately more powerful source of energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we’re stuck with the inferior fuel and despite the fact that the planet is in danger from the effects of our greed, no government, company or person is willing to spend the money to build new traditional reactors, let alone developing an entirely new one with a non-existent fuel supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with nuclear power ends up being, not about the energy source itself but, about the stigma surrounding it. No person or company is willing to sacrifice their public image, and no government official is willing to possibly sacrifice their position of power, to take a stand and spend the initial money to build new reactors or develop new technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/tokamak-4k.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;nuclear-fusion&#34;&gt;Nuclear Fusion.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point it may seem hard to fathom that nuclear energy could ever get more attractive than thorium salt reactors but while the Meitner team in Berlin were investigating fission; in 1932 fusion, the combining of two nuclei to form a new element, had been discovered by Mark Oliphant as part of a 50 year study into what powered stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fusion is the same process as what happens at the centre of the sun and every other star in the universe, this is achieved when a gas cloud forms and a slight gravity occurs, this will cause the gas to pack more tightly. The gas keeps getting denser until fusion begins to occur which dramatically heats up the elements in what is now a star.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here on earth, the most reliable way to achieve fusion is to use deuterium, an isotope of hydrogen, which is more than abundant here on earth. After pulling the best vacuum that you can manage on your reaction chamber, it’s time to fill it with deuterium and heat the chamber while pressurizing it as much as possible. When there is enough heat and pressure, the atoms inside will start to hit each other and some will fuse to make helium, giving off a little bit of energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fusion is the holy grail of energy and there are many ways of achieving it, best of all it would be cheap, safe and produces a negligible amount of waste with a half-life of just minutes. Unfortunately, the same property of fusion which makes it safe is also what is holding us back; fusion is not a self-sustaining reaction like fission; at the moment it is taking far more energy to sustain the reaction than the reaction is producing. This property means that fusion could never create any sort of nuclear explosion but it also means that it is very hard to make fusion worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are already many thousands of scientists around the world and many billions of dollars of investment going into nuclear fusion all of which is going at the problem in many different ways all of which have different methods of heating the material to the most extreme temperatures possible and any of these methods could be the way to achieve a sustained reaction where it produces more power than it uses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/sunset-lake-reflections-4k.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-conclusion&#34;&gt;In Conclusion.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that we should immediately divert funds from less clean means of energy including wind and solar energy into constructing new nuclear power plants which are designed from the ground up to be safe, they should in any imaginable event be able to automatically shut themselves down despite a lack of power or human intervention. These measures should make the plants considerably safer and allow them to take over all of the power supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of this, despite the redundancy we build in our reactors, we should also create a much more robust stance on the culture of safety within the institutions that run our nuclear power plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we need to begin funding research into thorium salt reactors which I estimate would be able to start construction in around 10 years, this should secure our energy needs for hundreds if not thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lastly we should continue to invest heavily into nuclear fusion experiments, if we achieve a sustainable reaction then our energy supply is guaranteed for the longest foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people seem to think that nuclear energy is an old and dying form of energy supply, but this is far from the truth; nuclear energy is the future, it is the way forward. If we want to survive on this planet for even fifty more years then we need to make a drastic, swift and decisive move towards nuclear energy, the survival of our species depends on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Chico Demmenie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thelancet.com/article/S0140-6736(07)61253-7/abstract&#34;&gt;Markandya A. &amp;amp; Wilkinson P. 2007 &amp;ldquo;Electricity generation and health.&amp;rdquo; The Lancet. 370 (9591) Pages 979-990&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.columbia.edu/~jeh1/mailings/2016/CaoJ.China-U.S._cooperation_to_advance_nuclear_power.Science.2016.pdf&#34;&gt;China-US Cooperation to advance Nuclear power.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Re-Uploaded &amp;amp; Edited 30/09/2022]&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
