<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics on Mirantibus</title>
    <link>/tags/politics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Politics on Mirantibus</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 21:59:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Climate Crisis Response.</title>
      <link>/posts/the-climate-crisis-response/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 21:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/the-climate-crisis-response/</guid>
      <description>In a small bay, on the northern side of the southwestern tip of England, not too far from lands&amp;rsquo; end. The usually quiet and quaint town of Hayle has become a flurry of activity with Boris Johnson hosting 7 other countries and representatives from the EU and UN for informal talks in order to address the day&amp;rsquo;s issues. By far the most important issue this year, as in other recent years; is the climate crisis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The good in us all: why we should trust people more.</title>
      <link>/posts/the-good-in-us-all/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2020 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/the-good-in-us-all/</guid>
      <description>Recently I read a book by the Dutch historian Rutger Bregman, called &amp;ldquo;Human Kind: A hopeful history&amp;rdquo;. The book is about human nature, the underlying features that shape us and how we are affected by civilisation or perhaps how civilisation is shaped by our nature. The book systematically goes through each aspect of human nature, each example of our collective nature that you may think is true and then shows you how it can be reversed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going Nuclear.</title>
      <link>/posts/going_nuclear/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/going_nuclear/</guid>
      <description>Today we will be looking at the history of nuclear energy and how it may help us in the future. From the discovery of nuclear fission to its more attractive cousin: nuclear fusion, today we learn the ins and outs of the atomic realm.
Nuclear Fission, a short history. Let’s start our journey with possibly one of the most important discoveries of the 20th century: Nuclear Fission. Nuclear Fission was first discovered in 1938 in Berlin after 50 years of research into radioactivity, which naturally broadened into what is now known as nuclear physics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
